I want to start with a story, a la Seth Godin,
أود أن أبدأ بقصة، ألاساس غودين،
from when I was 12 years old.
منذ أن كان عمري 12 عاماً.
My uncle Ed gave me a beautiful blue sweater --
أعطاني عمي "آد" معطفاً جميلاً أزرق اللون--
at least I thought it was beautiful.
على الأقل أعتبرته جميلاً.
And it had fuzzy zebras walking across the stomach,
وكان عليه حمير وحشية غامضة تسير قرب المعدة،
and Mount Kilimanjaro and Mount Meru were kind of
وكان جبل كلمنجارو وجبل ميرو تقريباً
right across the chest, that were also fuzzy.
بقرب الكتف، كان ذلك غامضاً أيضاً.
And I wore it whenever I could,
وكنت أرتديه وقتما أستطيع،
thinking it was the most fabulous thing I owned.
معتقدةً أنه كان أروع شئ أقتنيته.
Until one day in ninth grade,
حتى في أحد الأيام كنت في الصف التاسع،
when I was standing with a number of the football players.
بينما كنت أقف مع عدد من لاعبي كرة القدم.
And my body had clearly changed, and Matt,
وكان جسمي قد تغيّر بوضوح، و"مات ميوسولينا"،
who was undeniably my nemesis in high school,
الذي كان بلا شك عدو لي في المدرسة الثانوية ،
said in a booming voice that
قال بصوت مزعج أننا
we no longer had to go far away to go on ski trips,
لم يعد علينا للذهاب بعيدا لرحلات التزلج على الجليد ،
but we could all ski on Mount Novogratz.
بل يمكننا جميعاً التزلج على جبل نوفوغراتس.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I was so humiliated and mortified
وقد شعرت بالاذلال والخزي
that I immediately ran home to my mother and chastised her
بحيث ركضت على الفور للبيت لأمي وأنتقدها
for ever letting me wear the hideous sweater.
للسماح لي بلبس المعطف البشع.
We drove to the Goodwill and we threw the sweater away
قدنا السيارة إلى مؤسسة النوايا الحسنة ورمينا المعطف بعيداً
somewhat ceremoniously,
بطريقة إحتفالية،
my idea being that I would never have to think about the sweater
فكرتي كانت أنني لن أحتاج للتفكير مجدداً بالمعطف
nor see it ever again.
أو أن أراه مجدداً البتة.
Fast forward -- 11 years later, I'm a 25-year-old kid.
تقدم سريع -- لاحقاً بعد 11 عاماً، عمري 25 سنة.
I'm working in Kigali, Rwanda, jogging through the steep slopes,
أنا أعمل في كيغالي، رواندا، أجري عبر المنحدرات الشديدة،
when I see, 10 feet in front of me, a little boy -- 11 years old --
حينما أرى أمامي، طفل صغير طوله 10 أقدام -- عمره 11 سنة--
running toward me, wearing my sweater.
يجري أمامي، يلبس معطفي.
And I'm thinking, no, this is not possible.
وأنا أفكر، لا، هذا ليس ممكناً.
But so, curious, I run up to the child -- of course
لكن بكل فضول، جريت إلى الطفل -- بالطبع
scaring the living bejesus out of him --
مرعبةً إياه --
grab him by the collar, turn it over, and there is my name
سحبته من الياقة، قلبتها، وكان أسمي
written on the collar of this sweater.
مكتوب على ياقة المعطف.
I tell that story, because it has served and continues to serve
أنا أقص تلك القصة، لأنها خدمت وما تزال تخدم
as a metaphor to me about the level of connectedness
بمثابة مجاز بالنسبة لي حول مستوى الترابط
that we all have on this Earth.
الذي لدينا جميعاً على هذه الأرض.
We so often don't realize what our action and our inaction
نحن في أغلب الأحيان لا ندرك ما تفعله حركاتنا وسكناتنا
does to people we think we will never see and never know.
للناس الذين نعتقد أننا لن نراهم ولن نعرفهم مطلقاً.
I also tell it because it tells a larger contextual story
أنا أيضاً أقصها لأنها تخبر عن قصة في سياق أكبر
of what aid is and can be.
عن ما يمكن أن تكون المساعدات.
That this traveled into the Goodwill in Virginia,
أن هذا أنتقل إلى مؤسسة النوايا الحسنة في فيرجينيا،
and moved its way into the larger industry,
وشق طريقه إلى قطاع أكبر،
which at that point was giving millions of tons of secondhand clothing to Africa and Asia.
الذي كان في تلك النقطة تقديم ملايين الأطنان من الملابس المستعملة إلى أفريقيا وآسيا.
Which was a very good thing, providing low cost clothing.
الذي كان شيئاً جيداً للغاية، تقديم ملابس منخفضة القيمة.
And at the same time, certainly in Rwanda,
وفي نفس الوقت، بالتحديد في رواندا،
it destroyed the local retailing industry.
فانها دمرت قطاع تجارة التجزئة المحلي.
Not to say that it shouldn't have,
لا أقول أنها لم تفعل ذلك،
but that we have to get better at answering the questions
لكن أننا ينبغي أن نكون أفضل في إجابة الأسئلة
that need to be considered when we think about consequences
التي نحتاج لوضعها في الإعتبار عندما نفكر بالتبعات
and responses.
والإستجابات.
So, I'm going to stick in Rwanda, circa 1985, 1986,
لذا، سأظل في رواندا، سيركا 1985، 1986،
where I was doing two things.
حيث كنت أفعل شيئين.
I had started a bakery with 20 unwed mothers.
لقد بدأت مخبزاً مع 20 من الأمهات غير المتزوجات.
We were called the "Bad News Bears," and our notion was
كنا نسمى دببة الأخبار السيئة، وكانت فكرتنا
we were going to corner the snack food business in Kigali,
بأننا سنقوم باحتكار سوق المأكولات الخفيفة في كيغالي،
which was not hard because there were no snacks before us.
الذي لم يكن صعباً لأنه لم توجد وجبات خفيفة قبلنا.
And because we had a good business model, we actually did it,
ولأنه كان لدينا نموذج أعمال جيد، لقد فعلنا هذا في الواقع،
and I watched these women transform on a micro-level.
وقد رأيت اؤلئك النسوة يتحولن إلى المستوى الجزئي.
But at the same time, I started a micro-finance bank,
لكن في نفس الوقت، بدأت بنك للتمويل الجزئي،
and tomorrow Iqbal Quadir is going to talk about Grameen,
وغداً سيتحدث إقبال غوادير عن غرامين،
which is the grandfather of all micro-finance banks,
الذي هو عراب كل بنوك التمويل الجزئي،
which now is a worldwide movement -- you talk about a meme --
التي هي الآن حركة عالمية -- تتحدثون عن ميمي--
but then it was quite new, especially in an economy
لكن حينها كانت حديثة جداً، خاصةً في إقتصاد
that was moving from barter into trade.
كانت يتحول من المقايضة إلى التجارة.
We got a lot of things right.
نفذنا الكثير من الأشياء بصورة صحيحة.
We focused on a business model; we insisted on skin in the game.
ركزنا على نموذج أعمال، وعلى الأفراد في اللعبة.
The women made their own decisions at the end of the day
قامت النسوة بإتخاذ قرارهن في نهاية اليوم
as to how they would use this access to credit
حول كيف يستخدمن هذه الفرصة للإقتراض
to build their little businesses, earn more income
لنباء عملهم الصغير، وكسب مداخيل أكثر
so they could take care of their families better.
بحيث يستطعن العناية بأسرهن بصورة أفضل.
What we didn't understand, what was happening all around us,
ما لم نكن نفهمه، ما كنا يجري حولنا،
with the confluence of fear, ethnic strife
مع إقتران الخوف، الصراعات العرقية
and certainly an aid game, if you will, that was playing into
وبالتأكيد لعبة المساعدات، إن شئتم، التي كانت تدور في
this invisible but certainly palpable movement inside Rwanda,
هذه الحركة الخفية لكنها واضحة داخل رواندا،
that at that time, 30 percent of the budget was all foreign aid.
بحيث أنه في ذلك الوقت، 30 في المائة من الميزانية كانت من المساعدات الأجنبية.
The genocide happened in 1994,
حدثت الإبادة الجماعية في عام 1994،
seven years after these women all worked together
سبعة أعوام بعد أن عملت اؤلئك النسوة سوياً
to build this dream.
لبناء هذا الحلم..
And the good news was that the institution,
والأخبار الجيدة كانت تلك المؤسسة،
the banking institution, lasted.
مؤسسة البنك، هي التي صمدت
In fact, it became the largest rehabilitation lender in the country.
في الحقيقة، لقد أصبحت أكبر البنوك لإعادة الإعمار في البلاد.
The bakery was completely wiped out,
كان المخبز قد قضي عليه تماماً،
but the lessons for me were that accountability counts --
لكن الدروس كانت أن المحاسبة مهمة --
got to build things with people on the ground,
بنينا الأشياء مع الناس على الأرض،
using business models where, as Steven Levitt would say,
بإستخدام نماذج أعمال حيث، كما سيقول إستيفن ليفيت،
the incentives matter.
المحفزات مهمة.
Understand, however complex we may be, incentives matter.
فهم كم التعقيدات التي قد تحدث، المحفزات مهمة.
So when Chris raised to me how wonderful everything
لذا عندما أشار لي "كريس" كم هو رائع كل شئ
that was happening in the world,
كان يحدث في العالم،
that we were seeing a shift in zeitgeist,
بحيث أننا نشهد تحولاً في روح العصر،
on the one hand I absolutely agree with him,
في جانب أنا أتفق معه كلياً،
and I was so thrilled to see what happened with the G8 --
وقد كنت مثارة جداً لرؤية ما حدث مع قمة الثمانية --
that the world, because of people like Tony Blair and Bono
أن العالم، بسبب أناس مثل توني بلير و بونو
and Bob Geldof -- the world is talking about global poverty;
وبوب غيلدوف -- يتحدث العالم عن الفقر العالمي،
the world is talking about Africa
يتحدث العالم عن أفريقيا
in ways I have never seen in my life.
بطريقة لم أشهدها مطلقاً طوال حياتي.
It's thrilling.
إنها مثيرة.
And at the same time, what keeps me up at night
وفي نفس الوقت، ما يسهرني في الليل
is a fear that we'll look at the victories of the G8 --
هو الخوف من أننا سننظر في النصر من قمة الثمانية --
50 billion dollars in increased aid to Africa,
50 مليار دولار زيادة من المساعدات إلى أفريقيا،
40 billion in reduced debt -- as the victory,
40 مليار دولار خفض للديون -- ننظر لها كنصر،
as more than chapter one, as our moral absolution.
أكثر من الفصل الأول، كمغفرة لأخلاقنا.
And in fact, what we need to do is see that as chapter one,
وفي الحقيقة، ما علينا فعله هو أن نرى ذلك كالفصل الأول،
celebrate it, close it, and recognize that we need a chapter two
نحتفي به، نغلقه، ونقرّ بأننا نحتاج للفصل الثاني
that is all about execution, all about the how-to.
كل ذلك عن التنفيذ -- كل شئ عن الكيفية.
And if you remember one thing from what I want to talk about today,
وإن كنتم تذكرون شيئاً واحداً مما أريد الحديث عنه اليوم،
it's that the only way to end poverty, to make it history,
هو أن الطريقة الوحيدة لإنهاء الفقر، لجعله تاريخاً،
is to build viable systems on the ground
هو ببناء أنظمة قادرة على البقاء على الأرض
that deliver critical and affordable goods and services to the poor,
ترسل بضائع حرجة وبأسعار معقولة وخدمات للفقراء،
in ways that are financially sustainable and scaleable.
بطريقة تكون مستدامة مالياً وتستوعب الحجم.
If we do that, we really can make poverty history.
إذا فعلنا ذلك، يمكننا حقاً جعل الفقر كتاريخ.
And it was that -- that whole philosophy --
وقد كان ذلك -- كل تلك الفلسفة--
that encouraged me to start my current endeavor
التي شجعتني لبداية مسعاي الحالي
called "Acumen Fund,"
الذي يسمى صندوق أكيومن ،
which is trying to build some mini-blueprints
الذي هو محاولة لبناء بعض المخططات الصغيرة
for how we might do that in water, health and housing
لكيفية فعل ذلك في الماء، الصحة والإسكان
in Pakistan, India, Kenya, Tanzania and Egypt.
في باكستان، الهند، كينيا، تنزانيا و مصر.
And I want to talk a little bit about that, and some of the examples,
وأريد الحديث قليلاً حول ذلك، وبعض الأمثلة
so you can see what it is that we're doing.
بحيث يمكنكم رؤية ما نقوم بفعله.
But before I do this -- and this is another one of my pet peeves --
لكن قبل أن أفعل ذلك -- وهذا شئ آخر يضايقني --
I want to talk a little bit about who the poor are.
أرغب بالحديث قليلاً عن من هم الفقراء.
Because we too often talk about them as these
لأننا أيضاً نتحدث عنهم دائماً كهؤلاء
strong, huge masses of people yearning to be free,
الجموع القوية الضخمة من الناس الساعين للحرية،
when in fact, it's quite an amazing story.
بينما في الحقيقة، إنها قصة مذهلة للغاية.
On a macro level, four billion people on Earth make less than four dollars a day.
على المستوى الجزئي، أربعة مليارات شخص على الأرض يجنون أقل من أربعة دولارات يومياً.
That's who we talk about when we think about "the poor."
هؤلاء هم من نتحدث عنهم عندما نتحدث عن الفقراء.
If you aggregate it, it's the third largest economy on Earth,
وإن قمت بتجميعهم، فأنها ثالث أكبر إقتصاد على الأرض،
and yet most of these people go invisible.
ولكن معظم هؤلاء الناس غير مرئيين.
Where we typically work, there's people making between
حيث نعمل عادةً، هناك أناس يجنون بين
one and three dollars a day.
دولار إلى ثلاثة دولارات يومياً.
Who are these people?
من هم أؤلئك الناس؟
They are farmers and factory workers.
إنهم المزارعون وعمال المصانع.
They work in government offices. They're drivers.
إنهم يعملون في المكاتب الحكومية. إنهم سائقون.
They are domestics.
إنهم خدم المنازل.
They typically pay for critical goods and services like water,
إنها يدفعون فقط للسلع الحرجة والخدمات مثل الماء،
like healthcare, like housing, and they pay 30 to 40 times
مثل الرعاية الصحية، مثل الإسكان، ويدفعون 30 إلى 40 مرة
what their middleclass counterparts pay --
ما يدفعه نظرائهم من الطبقة الوسطى--
certainly where we work in Karachi and Nairobi.
بالتأكيد حيث نعمل في كراتشي ونيروبي.
The poor also are willing to make, and do make, smart decisions,
ويرغب الفقراء كذلك في أخذ وتنفيذ قرارات ذكية،
if you give them that opportunity.
إن قمت بتقديم الفرصة لهم.
So, two examples.
إذاً ، مثالين.
One is in India, where there are 240 million farmers,
الأول في الهند، حيث هناك 240 مليون مزارع،
most of whom make less than two dollars a day.
معظمهم يجني أقل من دولارين يومياً.
Where we work in Aurangabad, the land is extraordinarily parched.
حيث نعمل نحن في أورانج اباد، فأن الأرض جافة بصورة غير عادية.
You see people on average making 60 cents to a dollar.
ترى الناس في المتوسط يجنون 60 سنتاً إلى دولار.
This guy in pink is a social entrepreneur named Ami Tabar.
هذا الشخص باللون الوردي هو رجل أعمال إجتماعي يسمى آمي تابار.
What he did was see what was happening in Israel, larger approaches,
ما فعله كان رؤية ما يحدث في إسرائيل، مقاربة أكبر،
and figure out how to do a drip irrigation,
ومعرفة كيفية تنفيذ الريّ بالتنقيط،
which is a way of bringing water directly to the plant stock.
التي هي طريقة لجلب الماء مباشرة إلى المخزون النباتي.
But previously it's only been created for large-scale farms,
لكن في السابق كانت تحدث فقط للمزارع ذات الأحجام الكبيرة،
so Ami Tabar took this and modularized it down to an eighth of an acre.
إذاً أخذ آمي تابار هذا وقام بتنميطه إلى ثُمن الفدان.
A couple of principles:
عدد من المبادئ --
build small.
بناء صغير.
Make it infinitely expandable and affordable to the poor.
أجعلها لا نهائية ومتوسعة ومعقولة السعر للفقراء.
This family, Sarita and her husband, bought a 15-dollar unit
هذه الأسرة، ساريتا وزوجها، أشتروا وحدة مقابل 15 دولار
when they were living in a -- literally a three-walled lean-to
عندما كانوا يعيشون في -- حرفياً ثلاثة جدران لينة
with a corrugated iron roof.
مع سقف حديدي .
After one harvest, they had increased their income enough
بعد حصاد واحد، قاموا بزيادة دخلهم بما يكفي
to buy a second system to do their full quarter-acre.
لشراء نظام ثاني لتنفيذ ربع كامل من الفدان.
A couple of years later, I meet them.
بعد عدة سنوات، إلتقيتهم.
They now make four dollars a day, which is pretty much middle class for India,
إنهم يجنون الآن أربعة دولارات يومياً، الذي هو في الغالب طبقة وسطى بالنسبة للهند،
and they showed me the concrete foundation they had just laid
ولقد رأيت اساس منزلهم البيتوني الذي صبوه مؤخراً
to build their house.
لبناء منزلهم.
And I swear, you could see the future in that woman's eyes.
وأنا أقسم، يمكنكم رؤية المستقبل في عيون هذه المرأة.
Something I truly believe.
الشئ الذي أؤمن فيه بشدة.
You can't talk about poverty today without talking about malaria bed nets,
لا يمكنك الحديث عن الفقر اليوم بدون الحديث عن ناموسيات الملاريا للسرير،
and I again give Jeffrey Sachs of Harvard
ومجدداً أنا أعطي جيفري ساشس من جامعة هارفارد
huge kudos for bringing to the world
مجداً كبيراً لتقديمه للعالم
this notion of his rage -- for five dollars you can save a life.
هذه الفكرة جراء غضبه -- لخمسة دولارات يمكن أن تنقذ حياة.
Malaria is a disease that kills one to three million people a year.
الملاريا هي مرض يقتل واحد إلى ثلاثة ملايين شخص سنوياً.
300 to 500 million cases are reported.
300 إلى 500 مليون حالة يتم الإبلاغ عنها.
It's estimated that Africa loses
لقد تم تقدير أن أفريقيا تخسر
about 13 billion dollars a year to the disease.
حوالي 13 مليار دولار سنوياً أمام هذا المرض.
Five dollars can save a life.
خمسة دولارات يمكن أن تنقذ حياة.
We can send people to the moon; we can see if there's life on Mars --
يمكننا إرسال الناس إلى القمر، يمكننا رؤية إن كان هناك حياة على المريخ--
why can't we get five-dollar nets to 500 million people?
لم لا نستطيع الحصول على ناموسية سعرها خمس دولارات لخمسمائة مليون شخص؟
The question, though, is not "Why can't we?"
السؤال، فضلاً عن هذا، ليس لم لا نستطيع،
The question is how can we help Africans do this for themselves?
السؤال هو كيف يمكننا مساعدة الأفارقة لفعل هذا بأنفسهم؟
A lot of hurdles.
الكثير من العقبات.
One: production is too low. Two: price is too high.
أولاً: الإنتاج منخفض للغاية. ثانياً: الأسعار عالية جداً.
Three: this is a good road in -- right near where our factory is located.
ثالثاً: هذا طريق جيد في -- تماماً بالقرب من حيث موقع مصنعنا.
Distribution is a nightmare, but not impossible.
التوزيع عبارة عن كابوس، لكنه ليس مستحيلاً.
We started by making a 350,000-dollar loan
لقد بدأنا بتوفير قرض بقيمة 350،000 دولار
to the largest traditional bed net manufacturer in Africa
لأكبر مُصنّع ناموسيات تقليدية في أفريقيا
so that they could transfer technology from Japan
بحيث يمكننا يمكنه نقل تكنلوجيا من اليابان
and build these long-lasting, five-year nets.
وبناء هذه الناموسيات التي تعيش طويلاً لمدة خمس سنوات.
Here are just some pictures of the factory.
هذه بعض الصور من المصنع.
Today, three years later, the company has employed
اليوم، بعد ثلاث سنوات، وظفت الشركة
another thousand women.
ألف من النسوة إضافيين.
It contributes about 600,000 dollars in wages to the economy of Tanzania.
وهو يسهم بحوالي 600،000 دولار من الأجور في تنزانيا.
It's the largest company in Tanzania.
إنه أكبر شركة في تنزانيا.
The throughput rate right now is 1.5 million nets,
معدل الإنتاجية حالياً هو 1.5 مليون ناموسية،
three million by the end of the year.
ثلاثة ملايين بنهاية هذه السنة.
We hope to have seven million at the end of next year.
نحن نأمل بالوصول لسبعة ملايين بنهاية العام المقبل.
So the production side is working.
إذاً فجانب الإنتاج يعمل.
On the distribution side, though,
لكن على جانب التوزيع،
as a world, we have a lot of work to do.
نحن كعالم، لدينا الكثير لنفعله.
Right now, 95 percent of these nets are being bought by the U.N.,
حالياً، 95 في المائة من هذه الناموسيات يتم شراؤها عبر الأمم المتحدة،
and then given primarily to people around Africa.
ثم يتم تقديمها في الأساس للناس حول أفريقيا.
We're looking at building
نحن ننظر في البناء
on some of the most precious resources of Africa: people.
على بعض أقيّم الموارد في أفريقيا -- الناس.
Their women.
نساء أفريقيا.
And so I want you to meet Jacqueline,
ولذا أرغب في مقابلة جاكولين،
my namesake, 21 years old.
نفس أسمي، 21 عاماً.
If she were born anywhere else but Tanzania,
إن كانت مولودة في أي مكان آخر سوى تنزانيا،
I'm telling you, she could run Wall Street.
أنا أخبركم، يمكنها إدارة وول إستريت.
She runs two of the lines, and has already saved enough money
إنها تدير خطين، وقد وفرّت ما يكفي من المال
to put a down payment on her house.
لدفع مقدم لبيتها.
She makes about two dollars a day, is creating an education fund,
إنها تجني حوالي دولارين يومياً، تنشئ صندوقاً للتعليم،
and told me she is not marrying nor having children
وأخبرتني بأنها لن تتزوج أو تنجب أطفالاً
until these things are completed.
حتى تستكمل هذه الأشياء.
And so, when I told her about our idea --
ولذا، عندما أخبرتها بفكرتنا --
that maybe we could take a Tupperware model from the United States,
ذلك أننا ربما نأخذ نموذج تيوبروير من الولايات المتحدة،
and find a way for the women themselves to go out
ونجد طريقة للنساء أنفسهن للخروج
and sell these nets to others --
وبيع هذه الناموسيات للآخرين --
she quickly started calculating what she herself could make
بدأت سريعاً بحساب ما يمكنها أن تجني
and signed up.
وشاركت.
We took a lesson from IDEO, one of our favorite companies,
لقد أخذنا الدرس من IDEO(شركة تصميم وإبتكار)، أحد شركاتنا المفضلة،
and quickly did a prototyping on this,
وسرعان ما فعلنا هذا النموذج،
and took Jacqueline into the area where she lives.
وأخذنا جاكلين إلى المنطقة التي تعيش فيها.
She brought 10 of the women with whom she interacts
لقد جلبت 10 من النساء الذين تتعامل معهن
together to see if she could sell these nets, five dollars apiece,
سوياً لرؤية إذا كانت تستطيع بيع هذه الناموسيات، خمسة دولارات مقابل القطعة،
despite the fact that people say nobody will buy one,
رغماً عن حقيقة أن الناس يقولون أنه لا أحد سيشتري واحدة،
and we learned a lot about how you sell things.
وقد تعلمنا الكثير حول كيف تبيع الأشياء.
Not coming in with our own notions,
لا تأتي بفكرتك الخاصة،
because she didn't even talk about malaria until the very end.
لأنها لم تتحدث حتى عن الملاريا حتى قرب النهاية.
First, she talked about comfort, status, beauty.
أولاً ، لقد تحدثت عن الراحة، الوضع، الجمال.
These nets, she said, you put them on the floor, bugs leave your house.
هذه الناموسيات، كما قالت، أنت تضعهم على الأرض، تغادر الحشرات بيتك.
Children can sleep through the night;
يمكن للأطفال النوع طوال الليل،
the house looks beautiful; you hang them in the window.
ويبدو المنزل جميلاً، وتعلقهم على النافذة.
And we've started making curtains,
و لقد بدأنا في صنع الستائر،
and not only is it beautiful, but people can see status --
وليس فقط هي جميلة، لكن الناس يمكن أن يروها كوضع إجتماعي--
that you care about your children.
ذلك أنك تهتم بأطفالك.
Only then did she talk about saving your children's lives.
فقط حينها تحدثت عن حفظ أرواح الأطفال.
A lot of lessons to be learned in terms of how we sell
الكثير من الدروس يمكن تعلمها عن كيف نبيع
goods and services to the poor.
السلع والبضائع إلى الفقراء.
I want to end just by saying that there's enormous opportunity
أريد أن أختم بالقول بأن هناك فرصة مذهلة
to make poverty history.
لجعل الفقر تاريخاً.
To do it right, we have to build business models that matter,
لفعلها بصورة صحيحة، يمكننا بناء نماذج أعمال تهم،
that are scaleable and that work with Africans, Indians,
تتناسب في الحجم وتعمل مع الأفارقة، الهنود،
people all over the developing world
الناس في كل العالم النامي
who fit in this category, to do it themselves.
الذين يقعون في هذه الفئة، لفعلها بأنفسهم.
Because at the end of the day, it's about engagement.
لأنه في نهاية اليوم، الأمر حول الإرتباط.
It's about understanding that people really don't want handouts,
إنه حول فهم أن الناس بالفعل لا يريدون صدقات،
that they want to make their own decisions;
ذلك أنهم يريدون أخذ قراراتهم الخاصة،
they want to solve their own problems;
يريدون أن يحلوا مشاكلهم الخاصة،
and that by engaging with them,
وأنه عبر الإرتباط بهم،
not only do we create much more dignity for them,
ليس فقط نصنع الكثير من الكرامة لهم،
but for us as well.
بل لنا نحن أيضاً.
And so I urge all of you to think next time
وأنا أيضاً أحثّكم للتفكير في المرة القادمة
as to how to engage with this notion and this opportunity
بكيف تشاركون في هذه الفكرة وهذه الفرصة
that we all have -- to make poverty history --
التي لدينا جميعاً -- لجعل الفقر تاريخاً --
by really becoming part of the process
وأن نصبح حقيقةً جزء من العملية
and moving away from an us-and-them world,
ونذهب بعيداً من عالم "نحن" و "هم"،
and realizing that it's about all of us,
وندرك أن الأمر كله حول "نحن"،
and the kind of world that we, together, want to live in and share.
ونوع العالم الذي نحن، وسوياً، نريد أن نعيش فيه ونتقاسمه.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)